Leah: As we have already discussed coding
standards are essential when working with
a team, but how does this work in practice?
A developer team would initially meet to
agree the rules that they would need to
follow within their coding standards guide.
This could consist of one that already
exists and be used as a template or basis
for creating their own coding style guide.
There are style guides and tools for programming
languages, development environments, platforms,
frameworks, and content management systems.
Chris: Style guides
A main consideration for choosing an existing
style guide is the coding languages that are going
to be used, as there are different standards that
are written for different programming languages.
One of the most well used open sourced style guides
for code standards is the Airbnb style guide.
This includes style guides for JavaScript,
ES5, React, CSS, Sass, and Ruby.
It can be found on the GitHub platform and
is one of the most popular style guides.
Leah: There are other ‘style guides’, and these include:
• Codeguide
• Idiomatic
• Wikimedia
• Google
• WordPress
You can check out these websites on our
weblinks section for more information.
Chris: Tools
As source code needs to be clean, consistent, and easy to
maintain by existing developers, there are a number of tools
that can be used in conjunction with the coding standards.
For example, StyleLint finds and fixes problems
in code; the tool identifies and reports when the
code is not consistent with the coding standards.
It is easy to configure as the style guide is
added as the default coding standard and the
team can also add their own rules if needed.
Leah: Another example is a tool that
formats the code such as Prettier.
It is a library with a plugin that can be set to
format your code each time you save your changes.
It removes the original styling and makes sure
that all the outputted code is a consistent style.
Other tools that are commonly used include:
• EditorConfig
• JSCS
• JSHint
Chris: Official guides and standards
As well as open source style guides there are also
official guides and standards that can be referenced.
This can be useful for certain larger
programming languages that are commonly used with
proprietary software – some examples include:
• Microsoft .NET Framework
• Sun Systems
• Java Programming language
• C++ Programming language
Leah: Code review
A code review which is also known as a peer
review, is a form of software quality assurance.
It is when one or more of the developer team would
check each other’s source code in a given project.
Typical elements of a code review would be to include
which standards would be used, first passes, using a
ticketing system, run tests, check any changes made
and then complete the review with an in-depth pass.
Code reviews would speed up the process of the
project as this would ensure consistency and that
the standards are being met across the whole team.
Chris: Static analysis
Static analysis also known as Static Application Security
Testing [SAST], is a tool that is used to automatically
check code for weaknesses that may cause issues later on.
It finds potential quality issues in
the code before the program is run.
It would be used to find and fix vulnerabilities,
bugs, code errors, security risks, memory leaks,
null pointers, buffer overflow, and any violations of
the coding standard whilst the code is in a ‘static’
state [meaning whilst the code is not being run].
It is often used to comply with coding
guidelines and industry standard.
Typical elements of static analysis would involve,
writing code, running a static code analyser,
reviewing results, fixing any issues and then testing.
Leah: Examples of static analysis tools include:
• SonarQube
-
• Checkmarx SAST [CxSAST]
• Snyk Code, and
• Veracode Static Analysis.